firebase a suite of tools for building
apps and managing infrastructure on top
of google cloud platform it was founded
by james tamplin and andrew lee in 2011
after they discovered that developers
were using their chat software to manage
non-chat application data this inspired
them to create a real-time database a
json database that automatically stays
in sync with your front-end application
it was later expanded to support user
authentication and website hosting to
act as a complete backend as a service
in 2014 it was acquired by google where
it was further expanded with serverless
computing via cloud functions push
notifications via cloud messaging and
other google services like analytics and
admob in 2017 google acquired fabric
from twitter and also launched a new
document database called firestore to
support a wider range of applications
most importantly though firebase
provides software development kits for
virtually every platform to manage and
scale this infrastructure with little to
no back-end code to build a full stack
application right now create a free
firebase project then open up some code
for your favorite front-end platform
install the firebase sdk then connect it
to the cloud with your project
credentials once initialized you can
start interacting with your backend